# JUAN CARLOS URCIA BAREA

jcurciabarea@gmail.com · www.jcurciabarea.info

I am a motivated, diligent analyst with a passion for macroeconomics, finance, and political economy. My current work at Moody's centers on sovereign risk for governments in Latin America. I previously served as policy advisor to U.S. Senator Ben Cardin in Washington, DC. My skillset centers on economic and policy analysis, communication and teamwork, and constantly learning.

#### **EDUCATION**

**Princeton University** Princeton, NJ Master in Public Affairs | School of Public and International Affairs August 2020 to May 2022

**Brown University** Providence, RI Bachelor of Arts | History August 2013 to May 2017

#### **EMPLOYMENT**

Moody's Corporation

New York, NY Senior Ratings Associate | Sovereign Risk Group November 2024 to Present Ratings Associate | Sovereign Risk Group July 2022 to October 2024

- Analyze credit risk and manage ratings of issuers including Argentina, Costa Rica, Guatemala, Panama, Honduras, and Inter-American Development Bank focusing on macroeconomics, finance, and politics.
- Write and contribute to research publications covering relevant credit developments as well as credit profiles and ad-hoc pieces, plus Multilateral Development Bank, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Global Sovereign Outlooks.
- Communicate with government and MDB officials, investors, and stakeholders to maintain relationships, conduct research, and share assessments on credit profiles and developments.
- Participate and help organize delegation trips to World Bank/IMF Meetings, IADB Annual Meeting, and annual visits to issuer countries including Bahamas, Panama, Cayman Islands, Guatemala, and Aruba.
- Coauthored report on advanced economy sovereign debt issuance; assisted initial rating assessment of new frontier market sovereign; supported ESG taskforce to improve score consistency.
- Utilize software including Excel, Bloomberg, Haver Analytics, FactSet, Cartis, and Copilot AI for quantitative analysis, constructing databases, and creating data visualizations.

## **US Department of Commerce**

Princeton, NJ

Graduate Consultant | Office of the US Secretary of Commerce

August 2021 to January 2022

- Graduate capstone project to advise the Office of the Secretary on implementation of the CHIPS Act and how to design and leverage the National Semiconductor Technology Center (NSTC).
- Researched industry trends; interviewed Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company, Intel, academics, researchers, and defense analysts to gather information; organized class trip to Phoenix, Arizona.

#### **US Department of the Treasury**

Washington, DC

Graduate Intern | Office of International Financial Markets

May to August 2021

- Created a large database and heatmap dashboard in Excel tracking macroeconomic and financial risk indicators across various advanced economies and emerging markets, using source data from Haver Analytics.
- Wrote and circulated internal memos researching and summarizing theoretical macro-financial concepts such as sovereign-bank debt risks, housing market trends, sovereign dollar debt crises, and credit bubbles.

# US Senator Benjamin L. Cardin

Washington, DC

Legislative Correspondent

July 2018 to July 2020

Staff Assistant

September 2017 to June 2018

- Assisted in writing and managing legislation, including the Government Employee Fair Treatment Act (P.L.116-1), which became law guaranteeing back-pay for furloughed workers during government shutdowns.
- Led office research and recommendations on the 2018-2019 35-day federal government shutdown and COVID-19 unemployment insurance and state fiscal relief legislative efforts as part of the CARES Act.
- Researched and wrote recommendation memos for bills, resolutions, nominations, Dear Colleague letters, constituent issues, breaking developments, and other action items for the Senator.

## **US Senate Committee on Foreign Relations**

Intern | Ranking Member, Democratic Staff

July to August 2016

Washington, DC

- Researched and circulated press clips on Southeast Asia security and foreign aid issues.
- Prepared briefing materials for staff and committee members for hearings, meetings, and events.

# US Representative David N. Cicilline

Pawtucket, RI

Intern | Pawtucket District Office

May to July 2016

- Managed busy front office, organized and supervised district events, and logged constituent correspondence.
- Created an Excel database for major government and elected officials in Rhode Island for internal office use.

### The Walt Disney Company

Burbank, CA

Intern | Corporate Strategy and Business Development

June to August 2015

- Conducted a financial analysis of a merger between two telecommunications firms.
- Collaborated on group research and slide deck on the "smart" ad tech industry landscape.

#### **VOLUNTEERING AND COMMUNITY ACTIVITIES**

**Instituto Cervantes** | Member and Student (2023-Present)

• Study the Spanish language and participate in Spanish and Latin American cultural events and activities.

Volunteer Income Tax Assistance (VITA) | SPIA Chapter Co-Lead and Volunteer (2021-2022)

• Provided weekly tax filing services to low-income and disadvantaged residents of Mercer County, New Jersey.

SPIA First Generation and Low-Income (FLI) Students | Co-Lead and Co-Founder (2020-2022)

• Hosted FLI alumni for career talks and collaborate with university on programming for FLI students.

The Julis-Rabinowitz Center for Public Policy and Finance | Graduate Associate (2020-2022)

• Engaged in seminars on financial policy and economic history led by faculty and visiting experts.

## LANGUAGES AND NATIONALITIES

- English: Native/Fluent | Spanish: Advanced (C1) | Japanese: Elementary
- United States of America (citizen) | Spain (citizen)

#### RELEVANT GRADUATE COURSEWORK

# Economics and Finance Microeconomics — Professor Amy Craft Macroeconomics — Professor Gregor Jarosch Public Economics — Professor Henrik Kleven International Economics — Professor Silvia Weyerbrock Financial Management — Professor Adam Shrager Growth, Finance, Crises — Professor Ashoka Mody Macroeconomic Ideas — Professor Ashoka Mody Central Banking — Professor Alan Blinder Global Supply Chains — Professor Doyle Hodges

#### **Statistics**

Quantitative Analysis – Professor David Lee Econometrics I – Professor Jordan Matsudaira Econometrics II – Professor Alexandre Mas Program & Policy Evaluation – Professor Jean Grossman

#### **Politics**

Politics of Public Policy – Professor Andrew Moravcsik Domestic Politics – Professor Frances Lee The State – Professor Philip Pettit

## **SKILLS AND INTERESTS**

**Professional:** politics, economics, financial analysis, fiscal and debt metrics, statistical analysis, data visualization, graphic design, writing, editing, public speaking, event planning, customer service

**Software:** Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook, Copilot); Adobe Creative Suite (Photoshop, InDesign); Econometric Analysis (Stata, R); Financial Research (Bloomberg Terminal, Haver Analytics, FactSet); Programming (Python, Java, HTML/CSS); Communications (Slack, Signal, Zoom, Webex, Teams)

**Expertise:** macroeconomics, sovereign credit, fiscal policy, monetary policy, finance, capital markets, development, politics and international affairs, labor policy and unions

Interests: photography, drawing, computers, economics, politics, history, hiking, tennis, soccer